Finding Aid for the Doreen Gehry Nelson Method of Design-Based Learning (formerly City Building Education™) Records LSC.2239
UCLA Library Special Collections
Doreen Gehry Nelson Method of Design-Based Learning (formerly City Building Education™) records
1959-2014
UCLA Library Special Collections
Nelson, Doreen G.
LSC.2239
51.8 linear feet (93 document boxes, 5 record storage boxes, 10 flat boxes and 1 telescope box)
11 audiovisual carriers (10 videocassettes, 1 film strip)
16 born-digital carriers (16 optical discs)
8.3 linear feet (4 unprocessed record cartons, 3 unprocessed flat boxes, 2 unprocessed doc boxes)
2.83 Gigabytes (814 files, 53 folders) Files transferred from 12 optical discs.
Doreen Gehry Nelson, Professor of Education and Adjunct Professor in the College of Environmental Design at California Polytechnic University in Pomona and Professor of Design-Based Learning at Art Center College of Design in Pasadena began researching transfer of learning to develop an educational theory, methodology, and practical application for K-12 classroom teachers while working within the Los Angeles Unified School District. She founded the Center for City Building Education™ in 1974 where she pioneered the educational methodology Backwards Thinking™ which led to her development of the educational reform movement called The Doreen Gehry Nelson Method of Design-Based Learning. The collection spans from 1959-2014 and consists of the Center for City Building Education™ (CBE) administrative and research files which include 3,000 CBE slides created by the Office of Ray and Charles Eames, the Doreen Gehry Nelson Method of Design-Based Learning (DBL) California State Polytechnic University and Art Center College of Design files, and publications which document the creation, development, and international implementation of Nelson's educational theories and methodologies.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS DIGITAL AND AUDIO MATERIALS: This collection contains both processed and unprocessed digital and audio materials. Digital and audio materials are not currently available for access, unless otherwise noted in a Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note at the series and file levels. All requests to access processed digital and audio materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Doreen Gehry Nelson, 2014.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9975900373606533
Biography/History
Doreen Gehry Nelson, a public school teacher who was determined to improve the level of information retention by her students, and to promote their higher-level thinking skills, researched transfer of learning to develop an educational theory, methodology, and practical application for K-12 classroom teachers. She earned her Bachelor of Arts, Arts & Humanities and Elementary Teaching Credential at UCLA in 1959 under the mentorship of Corrine A. Seeds and began her teaching practice at what is today called the UCLA LAB School Corrine A. Seeds Campus. She earned her Master of Arts Degree in Educational Administration with Distinction from California State University, Northridge in 1971.
Early in her career, Nelson taught primary grades at Westminster Elementary School in Venice, California where she began implementing her educational theories and methodologies. Since 1969 she formalized and honed these techniques and focused on training K-12 public school teachers. In 1974 she established the Center for City Building Education™ in Los Angeles where she pioneered the educational methodology Backwards Thinking™ that reversed Benjamin Bloom's taxonomy by starting the learning process with creative thinking. Using the built environment as a metaphor for real-life learning, it was the first federally funded architects-in-schools program.
Nelson, born in Toronto, Canada, is the only sibling of architect Frank Gehry – an early advisor, collaborator, and teacher in the program. She was recognized by The New York Times in 1991 as one of the thirty most innovative educators in the United States, awarded lifetime Honorary Membership in the American Institute of Architects (AIA) in 1996, and received the 2006 California State University Wang Family Excellence Award.
Doreen Gehry Nelson is Professor of Education and Adjunct Professor in the College of Environmental Design at California Polytechnic University in Pomona and Professor of Design-Based Learning at Art Center College of Design in Pasadena. Her research areas in education include transfer of learning, long-term retention of learning, higher-level thinking skills, creativity, critical thinking, design thinking, and Backwards Thinking™. Her work as founder and director of the Center for City Building Education™ led to her development of the educational reform movement called The Doreen Gehry Nelson Method of Design-Based Learning.
Scope and Content
The Doreen Gehry Nelson Method of Design-Based Learning (formerly City Building Education™) records range in date from 1959-2014. The collection consists of the Center for City Building Education™ (CBE) administrative and research files which include 3,000 CBE slides created by the Office of Ray and Charles Eames, the Doreen Gehry Nelson Method of Design-Based Learning (DBL) California State Polytechnic University and Art Center College of Design files, and publications which document the creation, development, and international implementation of Nelson's educational theories and methodologies.
Organization and Arrangement
This collection has been arranged in the following series:
Series 1: Center City Building Education™ Files
Series 2: The Doreen Gehry Nelson Method of Design-Based Learning Files
Series 3: Publications
Related Material
Interview of Corinne A. Seeds [oral history transcript] / Corinne A. Seeds, interviewee. UCLA Oral History Department interview, 1963. UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California Los Angeles.
Nelson, Doreen G.
- Center for City Building Education™ Files
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  SERIES CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audiovisual materials in this collection will require assessment and possible digitization for safe access. To review these audiovisual materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
  - Historical documentation, 1971-2010
    SUBSERIES CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing. To access audiovisual materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
    Scope and Content
    This subseries includes Nelson's files concerning her foundation of City Building Education™ (CBE). Most of these records were previously contained in boxes marked "archives." The creator's existing roughly chronological order has been maintained as well as her file titles.
    - Frank Gehry and and Doreen Gehry Nelson, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Materials include a photocopy of a photo of Gehry Nelson and her brother, Frank Gehry teaching at the Smithsonian.
    - Open Space proposal, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      This Open Space proposal for the Broadway Elementary School and the community of Venice, California was created by the Open Space Board of Directors, of which Nelson was a member while she was a teacher at Westminster Elementary School and coordinator of Venice projects for Open Space, a non-profit educational development corporation. The Open Space Board was comprised of educators, parents, and urbanologists who embraced an environmental curriculum and believed that "...public schools are public resources to help shape communities and be shaped by communities."
    - A Documentation of the CBEP for the NEA and Humanities within the LAUSD, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
      Materials include four copies of A Documentation of the City Building Educational Program for the National Endowment of the Arts (NEA) and Humanities within the Los Angeles Unified School District. This documentation describes the aims and objectives of the City Building Program, funded by the Artists-In-Schools Program of the NEA jointly with the United States Office of Education, through the Los Angeles Unified School District. Two copies are a limited edition set of ten with full color original photographs. Documentation includes work with consultant Architect Frank Gehry, guest lecturer Dr. August Berger from East Los Angeles City College, and Charles Eames' documentation of project activities.
    - Press releases, 1971-1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Materials include press releases for The Center for City Building Educational Programs.
    - School newsletters, 1971-1986 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Materials include CBEP newsletters from school sites and school districts.
    - Correspondence, 1971-2012 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Materials include letters from Architect Frank Gehry, Los Angeles City Council, philanthropist David Rockefeller, Jr., Designer Charles Eames, California Assemblyman Howard L. Berman, California Senator Newton R. Russell, and Jonas Salk of the Salk Institute.
    - Photo release forms, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Materials include photo release forms for students of the first City Building class.
    - CBE Summer Teacher Orientation Workshop booklet, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Materials include one workshop booklet for the following project participants: Sulphur Springs Union School District, Compton Unified School District, Los Angeles Unified School District, and St. Augustine-By-The-Sea.
    - Documentation, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Documentation includes a brief summary of the CBEP, support from the Sulphur Springs community, a statement on the program's primary goals and educational philosophies, an outline of curriculum, and a response to the program's progress by Project Director Nelson.
    - CB stationery, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Materials include stationery samples from the CBEP stationery and the Environmental Goals Committee of the Los Angeles Region Goals Project. Graphic designer Marion Sampler of Victor Gruen and Associates gifted the letterhead design to CBE in 1974.
    - Letters of endorsement, 1973-1998 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Letters of endorsement include correspondence from sculptor Claes Oldenburg, David Rockefeller, Jr., Frank Gehry, Ray Eames, Alan Kay of Apple Computer, Inc., Member of the United States House of Representatives Mel Levine, graphic designer Sheila de Bretteville, artist Judy Chicago, Ms. magazine editor Phyllis Rosser, ABC Unified School District Superintendent Dr. Eugene Tucker, and United States Secretary of Education Richard W. Riley.
    - CBEP Decision Making Tools, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      This booklet includes major fundamentals of the program and models for CBEP activities.
    - CBE documents, 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Materials include correspondence from the Internal Revenue Service concerning CBEP status as a non-profit corporation.
    - CBE corporate (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Materials include CBE Board of Directors Minutes and sample letterhead and envelopes designed by artist Marion Sampler. The letterhead lists Board Members and Advisory Trustees such as Ray Eames, Frank Gehry, John Goodlad, Jonas Salk, and Gloria Steinem.
    - Original CBE prints, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Materials include graphic designer Frederick Usher's original prints for CBE curricular maps and flow charts.
    - CBE transparencies, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Materials include transparencies of graphic designer Frederick Usher's original CBE prints.
    - Doreen Nelson consulting booklet, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
      This consulting booklet describes Nelson's work for CBE with a focus on education, design, and creative thinking.
    - Registry of Charitable Trusts documentation, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Materials include correspondence, registration form, and CBEP Articles of Incorporation.
    - CCAIA correspondence, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      Materials include a letter from the California Council of the American Institute of Architects (CCAIA) President Ward W. Deems to Frank O. Gehry concerning his appointment as Chairman of the Environmental Awareness Committee. Doreen Nelson is listed as a committee member.
    - Film script binder, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Materials include a description of CBEP and notes on the Eames film.
    - Cells for film, circa 1975 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Materials include charts, copies of The Source newspaper and film cells designed by Nelson's students.
    - Signed release forms, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Signed release forms by parents allow permission for students to participate in film, still photographs, and video documentation of the CBEP.
    - CBEP's trustees, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Materials include a CBEP report, lists of Board of Directors, Members of the Corporation, and Advisory Trustees as well as correspondence from trustees.
    - CBE film narration, 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      One 7 1/2 inch audio reel.
      Audiovisual materials in this collection will require assessment and possible digitization for safe access. To review these audiovisual materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
      Materials include film narration by actor Alan Mandell on a 7 1/2 inch audio reel and billing statements for film and photography.
    - The Classroom as City charts, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
      These charts describe and illustrate CBE methodology including its system, structure, and process.
    - Theater book draft, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
      Materials include first draft handwritten and typed notes, narration, and student writing samples.
    - CBE celebration flyers, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Materials include four copies of "Homage to an Idea" Doreen Nelson and City Building's first decade party flyers.
    - Testimonials, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      Materials include correspondence of support for the CBEP from students, parents, educators, administrators, and public officials.
    - CBE Programs lists, 1979, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      Materials include CBE history, funding history, and overview of the program.
    - CBEP posters, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Materials include two CBEP posters that describe the program's philosophy, curriculum, and background.
    - CBE Teaches Transformation posters, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Materials include posters for Steps of Transformation and The Classroom as a City.
    - New York City Branch Office, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      Materials include correspondence and Articles of Incorporation concerning the corporation's application for authority to conduct activities in New York.
    - The Classroom as a City invite and slides, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
      Materials include invite for Nelson's presentation at the C.U.N.Y. graduate center and reproductions of slides.
    - CBE graphic of backwards thinking, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - CBE graphic of system, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - City Building vs. Traditional Education graphic, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - CBE info., 1981 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      Materials include documentation of "Los Angeles of the Past, Present and Future" exhibition at the Southern California Institute of Architecture.
    - Trainer's manual, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 9)
      Materials include one copy of The Teacher as Designer/Builder of Curriculum training manual for the CBEP at ABC Unified School District.
    - CBE Prospectus, 1981-1984 (Box 5, Folder 10-12)
      Materials include three copies of the CBE Prospectus used for numerous grant proposals which includes Nelson's long range plan for disseminating CBE.
    - Teacher Peer-Training - Lab Idea Bank, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 13)
      Materials include two copies of the CBE proposal for a Teacher Peer-Training Program and Lab/Idea Bank.
    - Los Angeles Children's Museum originals, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 14)
      Materials include correspondence, reports, and a personal statement by Nelson which describes her educational beliefs and how she envisions the role of the Museum.
    - CBEP info and envelopes, 1983-1984 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      Materials include CBE letterhead, envelopes, clippings, and a five page summary of CBE by Nelson.
    - Contract - book, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Materials include one Memorandum of Agreement between Nelson and the Publishing Center for Cultural Resources for a CBEP book.
    - Books - general, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Materials include contracts for CBEP books including City Building Education: A Way to Learn, Children's City Building Book and Transforming the City/A City in the Classroom.
    - Book copyright, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Materials include copyright registration certificates for the following publications: City Building Education: A Way to Learn, Manual for the City Building Educational Program: Architectural Consultant Edition, Manual for the City Building Educational Program, and Transforming the City: A City in the Classroom.
    - Utah Street brochure, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
      One brochure for the Community Building Laboratory at Utah Street School.
    - Tristram Shepard correspondence, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 6)
      Letters between Nelson and Shepard, head of the department at the Simon Langton Boys' School and a copy of Shepard's "Education by Design" case study.
    - Neutra, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 7)
      Correspondence from Dion Neutra to Nelson concerning her class's upcoming visit to his house.
    - Brian Sutton-Smith, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 8)
      One letter from Nelson to Brian Sutton-Smith of the Graduate School of Education at the University of Pennsylvania.
    - Neutra house, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 9)
      Materials include a Neutra class list and student evaluations of the class.
    - Eames tape (dupe) (Box 6, Folder 10)
      One audio cassette tape.
    - Open Charter School profile and mission, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 11)
      Materials include Los Angeles Open Charter School profile, mission, and "Thoughts on the Open School" essay by Alan Kay.
    - Publishers, 1994-1996 (Box 6, Folder 12)
      Materials include correspondence with Janis A. Donnaud.
    - Apple San Jose, 1993-1994 (Box 6, Folder 13)
      File contains correspondence with Alan Kay and San Jose State University Educator newsletters.
    - Hon AIA, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 14)
      Materials include correspondence concerning Nelson's election as an Honorary Member of The American Institute of Architects (AIA) and her Certificate of Commendation from the Los Angeles Chapter of the AIA.
    - Powerful Ideas catalog (Box 6, Folder 15)
      Three Powerful Ideas catalogs discuss the principles and strategies of Alan Kay and Seymour Papert.
    - Evaluations, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      Photocopies of evaluations of Nelson and Leslie Stoltz's CBE work include letters from students and United States Department of Education Secretary Richard W. Riley.
    - CBE website, 1998-2001 (Box 7, Folder 2-4)
      Folder 2: One photo master CD.
      Materials include a site map, slides, a photo master CD, a City Building Program History timeline, and a binder of overhead projector transparencies.
    - CBE archives member list, 2006 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      Materials include Nelson's handwritten list of items for the CBE archives and a list of teachers, staff, consultants, project participants, and advisory board members who served between 1972 and 2006.
    - Student cards, 2006-2007 (Box 7, Folder 6)
      Materials include letters of gratitude from CBE students and Nelson's Pasadena cohort.
    - In Memoriam: Bernard Zimmerman, 2009 (Box 7, Folder 7)
      Materials include an obituary for Zimmerman who helped establish Cal Poly Pomona's Department of Architecture.
    - Frederick Arthur Usher, Jr. obituary, 2009 (Box 7, Folder 8)
      This obituary from The Santa Barbara Independent describes the life of Usher, Jr. who worked with Charles Eames in the 1950s and designed Nelson's first book.
    - Shell Publishing, 2010 (Box 7, Folder 9)
      Materials include correspondence with Shell Publishing, an outline for "Project-based Learning for the 21st Century" and copies of Buck Institute for Education project planning forms.
  - Agencies and organizations
    This subseries includes correspondence and enclosures from agencies and organizations concerning CBE projects. Files are arranged in alphabetical order.
    - ABA (Box 8, Folder 1)
      Materials include correspondence with Charlotte C. Anderson of the American Bar Association (ABA) and Nelson's manuscript describing her City Building law project.
    - AIA (Box 8, Folder 2)
      Correspondence from the American Institute of Architects (AIA) includes Learning About the Built Environment Sourcebook for environmental education. This Sourcebook features the CBEP.
    - California Council for the Social Studies (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Children's Museum Los Angeles (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Cal Poly Pomona (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Fort Worth Museum (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Getty (J. Paul) Museum (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Global Perspectives (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Group for Environmental Education (Box 8, Folder 9)
      Correspondence includes letters from GEE's Alicia McGinley and Director Richard Saul Wurman, architect and CBEP Advisory Trustee.
    - Gruen, Victor (Found.) (Box 8, Folder 10)
      Materials include Victor Gruen Center for Environmental Planning workshop evaluations, brochures and a copy of Gruen's The Charter of Vienna.
    - John Simon Guggenheim Memorial (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Harvard University (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Houston Independent School District (Box 8, Folder 13)
      This file contains letters from Associate Professor Peter C. Papademetriou, Rice University School of Architecture.
    - ICSID '75 Moscow (Box 8, Folder 14)
      Materials include correspondence from Yuri Soloview concerning Nelson's participation in the International Council of Societies of Industrial Design (ICSID) Congress.
    - Independent Curators, Inc. (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Institute for Development of Educational Ideas, Inc. (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - JDR 3rd (Box 8, Folder 17)
      Materials include correspondence from the John D. Rockefeller, 3rd Fund and An Arts In Education Source Book: A View from the JDR 3rd Fund.
    - Learning About Learning (Box 8, Folder 18)
      Correspondence includes letters from Learning About Learning Educational Foundation Director Jearnine Wagner.
    - Learning Magazine (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Los Angeles City Schools (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - L.A. Contemporary Art Museum (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Mark Taper Forum (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Museum of Contemporary Art (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Ms. Magazine (Box 9, Folder 4)
      Materials include correspondence with Phyllis F. Rosser and Gloria Steinem's typewritten thoughts on transformational moments and techniques.
    - National Endowment for the Arts (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Norwalk-La Mirada Unified School District (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Pepperdine University (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Piedmont Citizens for Action (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Rockefeller Foundation (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - SimCity 3000 (Box 9, Folder 10)
      Materials include the SimCity 3000 Teacher's Guide by Doreen Nelson and Leslie Stoltz.
    - Smithsonian (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - UCLA Graduate School of Management (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - U.S.C. (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - U.S.O.E. (Box 9, Folder 14)
      Materials include correspondence from Gerald W. Elbers, United States Office of Education.